hey everyone Dave here uh so recently I
had the unique experience of
participating in a screening of pet scop
and a short Q&A afterwards at uh a place
called spectacle uh which is a theater
in Brooklyn um if you are ever in the
Williamsburg area I I highly recommend
checking out spectacle it's uh an
amazing spot for for uh curated
experimental
screenings um and I was fortunate enough
to participate in this Q&A uh with my
friend Liz Ryerson and uh Jordan fish as
well uh Liz has a great new um episode
of her podcast the blood zone now
available so um I'll include a link to
that in my video description um Jordan
does some interesting stuff as well so
um I believe uh he has a podcast about
the uh Cohen Brothers so um I'm going to
check that out when I get a chance that
sounds right up my alley um so if I can
find that I'll include that in the video
description as well but yeah spectacle
is amazing I really wish I had something
like that around here
um yeah um but I so this uh I think I'm
going to title this video revisiting pet
Scot because um
it's it was really interesting to watch
this in uh in its entirety on the big
screen um it was It was kind of
surreal uh and so I just want to revisit
the series and maybe share some
Reflections
on um how experiencing it in this way in
like a communal setting contrast with
how
um you know how many of us first
encountered it as a sort of a you know
series of cryptic uploads on YouTube um
watching pet scop unfold on YouTube kind
of felt like intimate and mysterious
like um you know like stumbling on a
secret corner of the internet um each
upload was like a fragment uh and it you
know it was perceived as a puzzle piece
that we sort of would dissect and and
discuss on like for example the pet scop
subreddit
um or later like engaging with the uh
pet scop Wiki as well and that was a
vital part of the experience because it
it had this sense of community and
Discovery it was truly one of those like
you had to be there type of moments in
Internet culture
um but seeing it all at once in a
theater um transform the experience
entirely for me like there's this
Collective energy that comes with a live
audience
and you know like the silence during
these tense moments um the occasional
sort of nervous laughter at the
particular the the uh creepy parts
um these these shared reactions uh add
kind of an emotional depth that's hard
to replicate when you're just watching
it you know in its original contacts at
home by yourself um or perhaps with a
friend um
what struck me the most though was how
different the pacing felt um on YouTube
pets got thrived on this fragmented
nature um and it had kind of a slow burn
effect this
anticipation between
uploads um but in the theater it becomes
this sort of
uninterrupted uh experience where all of
the themes and motifs kind of hit you
all at once uh it's it was almost
overwhelming but in a good way and it
made me notice certain things that I'd
missed before um not anything
terribly uh not any kind of like
enormous Revelation per se uh especially
if if you've watched my videos I might
I'm going to be talking about a lot of
the things that I have discussed before
but kind of just adding a bit more uh
context but um yeah it kind of hammered
a few things home for me for sure sure
um I mean before we go any further I
have to say that watching pet scop now
and reflecting on its themes
of uh control and manipulation and and
uh systemic incentives I really do think
it's a is a work I've called it systemic
horror I think that's a good term for it
um I can't help but feel just a little
bit Vindicated um because back when I
started talking about like 90s style
neoliberalism and its lingering effects
I I was widely panned for it um I was
widely paned for even talking about
history and politics in the context of
this like you know Creepy Pasta um which
is you know in some sense to be expected
right this is the internet but um you
know watching pet scop in its
entirety uh really did kind of hammer
home this it it kind of made me feel
Vindicated for discussing uh
neoliberalism and doing like a uh
materialist analysis of the work
um because I you know
um you know people acted like I was
connecting the dots uh connecting dots
that didn't really exist pcop like
deeply resonates with like a Marxist
critique of the capitalist econ economy
um because it captures the hollow logic
of systems designed to kind of
perpetuate themselves whether um where
individuals play certain roles in ways
that may seem rational at at face value
But ultimately kind of
reinforce alienation and harm
um and there are signs even in the very
first video um you know like Paul comes
across a sign like the first sign he
comes across and I'm literally talking
about a sign so um the text reads the
gift plane has closed indefinitely and
all Personnel have left if you are
unaware the gift plane provided homes to
over a hundred young pets um that
phrasing
immediately evokes the language of
austerity uh the closure of of a system
that once provided care and stability
reflects what happens when uh support
structures are gutted under the guise of
efficiency or necessity particularly
relevant at this moment in time right
now because we are hearing about all of
Trump's um you know cabinet picks and we
are hearing a lot of noise to the effect
of you know cutting certain um
government services uh getting rid of
the Department of Education for example
um some some things things that seem
fairly absurd and I don't believe are uh
going to be accomplished um especially
with this band of uh incompetent morons
being put in charge but we shall see
maybe I'll be eating my words I don't
know just enjoying a bit of coffee on
this uh gray Tuesday Morning um so bear
with
me um but yeah like um I I do feel
Vindicated because uh petscop is kind of
like a perfect metaphor uh especially
like the closure of the gift plane it's
like a perfect metaphor for the
austerity measures of neoliberalism uh
in the 90s where services are Stripped
Away leaving V you know leaving
vulnerable people to fend for themselves
all the while masking the
cruelty with this like thin of of
personal responsibility right um in
petscop as in life those Left Behind are
the ones who bear the consequences of of
these
policies um yeah so oh before diving any
deeper I do want to mention that pet
scops Creator Tony Dominico uh did not
attend the screening he was invited but
uh he didn't want to come for whatever
reason um but he did he did give his
approval along with uh the following
statement so this is quite interesting I
want you to pay attention to what uh
Tony has to say here if you're watching
this for the first time I recommend
treating it like a weird dream and not
straining yourself over details these
videos were released over the course of
several years and most viewers were
getting some kind of information from
elsewhere from YouTubers or from notes
compiled by the community to help them
make sense out of what was happening I
knew this and it affected the way I
chose to present or totally opusc basic
elements of the story like characters
imp plot so don't worry too much about
those things I hope you get something
out of
it pretty cool right uh pretty
interesting um kind of a lynchian
statement I I I I believe others have
made that comparison as well at the
screening um feels quite lynching you
know when when David Lynch is asked to
explain his work he just refuses to do
so
um but the
statement I guess I perceive it as both
an invitation and a challenge um it's a
reminder to kind of let go of the urge
to try to solve everything and just let
the experience wash over you um like a
dream right and yet it's funny because
petscop itself seems to comment on our
compulsion to solve puzzles it hence add
a deeper question what happens when we
try to solve something that isn't
necessarily meant to be solved um so
Paul the protagonist often treats pet
scop like a typical game he breezes past
dialogue and rushes to solve these like
bizarre logical puzzles in order to
progress further in the game at first
it's almost as if he doesn't fully
recognize the weight of what's happening
around him um maybe he's just kind of
too focused on the
mechanics and so as viewers we're
prompted to pause and try to try to um
read what Paul overlooks or try to
notice things that are ski past casually
um as if the game is inviting us to go
deeper than perhaps Paul is willing to
do uh but this does raise a bigger
question to me is the act of solving
these
puzzles perpetuating something
nefarious uh by understanding petscop is
a series of logical problems to
solve are we the audience like Paul
missing something important about its
emotional and uh thematic depth Paul's
puzzle solving approach might reflect a
kind of um
reductionism uh breaking the game down
into manageable logical Parts um but in
doing so he risks the the he risks
missing the bigger
picture or this emotional depth that's
encoded into like the cryptic dialogue
and the uh the environment itself right
like the big good grief and a l right
um it's it's as though his approach
mirrors our own Tendencies uh so it kind
of like holds up a mirror to how you
know we engage with media and and
perhaps sometimes life
itself um and it kind of reminds me of
the Divide we often see between stem
fields and the humanities there's a
tendency to view stem as focus on
solving practical problems with
precision and logic while human's
grapple with abstract um subjective
questions right
um but petscop illustrates why this
dichotomy is false and why it's
dangerous uh Paul's logical approach to
the game highlights the importance of
engaging with art from a
multi-disciplinary approach uh art is
not something to be solved um it's it's
something to be felt and inter
interpreted and and Revisited you know
um you can have a different
interpretation later in life if you you
know I I I do feel like my perspective
has shifted to some degree um since I
you know first started analyzing pet
scop so much has happened since then
right uh both uh both for me personally
and for um you know Society in general
you know um so it's I do feel like on
one hand I'm coming at it from a newer A
New Perspective but also it is kind of
um it is kind of vindicating things I
said previously or or certain threads
that I was trying to uh pull on so like
you know by combining the analytical
tools of stem with like the reflective
interpretive methods of the
humanities I think we can approach works
like pet scup with uh a more nuanced
approach um we can we can have a kind of
uh nuanced perspective on things and it
does tie into a larger question of
Ethics as well is there something
problematic about treating art and
perhaps people as well as mere logical
puzzles to be solved uh what what does
it mean to approach something in order
to like achieve Mastery over it versus
approaching it in order to try and
apprehend it as a work that's always in
progress knowing that you have to know
and accept that this understanding you
might have is inherently incomplete and
irreconcilable to some degree um petscop
seems to deliberately blur this line
especially when it comes to its themes
of uh you know surveillance
confinement and and control um
as the story unfolds it becomes clear
that Paul Bell and Marvin these
characters all play specific roles in a
process whereby the character care is
captured much like a Pokemon right and
and subjected to some kind of
transformation um so it does seem to be
a play on Pokemon with you know
capturing capturing a quote unquote pet
and and subjected to some kind of
transformation so those familiar with uh
you know Pokemon the game know that you
know you capture these things and level
them up and ideally you want them to
evolve into more powerful beings right
but uh pcop kind of uh adds a Twist to
this Dynamic right because um car as a
person and this character Marvin seems
to want to
uh transform her into something else
um yeah
so this isn't just like a gameplay
mechanic right it's a
metaphor um for control and
manipulation it suggests that some of
these characters are perhaps unwitting
participants in a system that's designed
to
perpetuate uh a kind of hellish process
of uh you know um kind of molding
somebody else uh into into something
that they are not in order to sort of
conform to your expectations right
um and it makes me wonder right like by
engaging with the
game is is the player somehow complicit
in this and by extension are we the
viewer
complicit just by observing and trying
to understand this
logic um it brings to mind Herbert
Marcus's one-dimensional man
particularly the idea of instrumental
reason and how systems can incentivize
behaviors that lead to unintended often
times um harmful consequences right uh
take the classic
example it's entirely rational for each
individual to want to leave work and go
home at the end of the day right if
you're
commuting but when everyone makes this
same rational Choice it can lead to a
traffic jam um so this is a systemic
problem uh that is born from
individually rational choices so the
problem is that the system is
incentivizing this right
um maruse argues that instrumental
reason when unchecked prioritizes the
logic of systems over individual or
Collective well-being and it becomes a
mechanism for
Domination by uh perpetuating the
existing power
structure similarly in petcot Paul might
well be operating within a system uh
that feels logical or um inevitable to
him yet is it possible his actions are
somehow feeding the system in a manner
that perpetuate some kind of negative
outcome it's an interesting question to
me uh as viewers we engage with pet scop
in a similar way we treat it as a puzzle
to be solved or a mystery that is we
unravel and by doing so we risk
perpetuating the same instrumental logic
uh focusing on decoding the game rather
than questioning its deeper systemic
implic uh systemic implications and um
you know ignoring the ideological
dimensions of of this uh of this
gameplay experience right um I think you
know I dare say a lot of the
interpretations on of pet scop on
YouTube are guil of this right they
fundamentally miss that this is systemic
horror that the game is a system uh that
is in some sense P perpetuating itself
and
um you really have to
analyze how the system of pcop
incentivizes the player to continue the
process uh to perpetuate
this kind of feedback loop
um I think it it you know it's relevant
to talk about the character Rainer in
this context whose real name is uh we
learn is Daniel Hammond um so he's the
creator of the in Universe game petscop
and early in the series Paul
speculates that the game wasn't made for
him um not him
specifically and there is evidence that
rer designed the game specifically for
Marvin possibly to accuse him of some
kind of heinous crime and subsequently
extract information from him um at first
it seems you know like later in the
series we see that Marvin this character
Marvin is testing the game perhaps
they've been tasked with doing so as
part of uh a broader effort of you know
to for Daniel to develop this game
um
and yeah rainer's actions seem driven by
a sense of guilt or complicity regarding
Marvin's Behavior so this this adds
layers of moral ambiguity to um rainer's
character is pcop a tool for
justice or
is this perhaps just rainer's way of
grappling with his own
complicity
um the game functions as a surveillance
system and I think that's a particularly
interesting aspect of this work uh the
game tracks the players every movement
and at one point it becomes clear that
Rainer has mapped elements of the game
um kind of based on a real world
location we don't exactly have access to
what this location where this location
is it's censored right um which is
another interesting Dynamic
but this prompts Marvin who you know is
testing the game at this point to um you
know it's trying to get him to reveal
perhaps where he buried something right
we are we are not exactly uh privy to
what is going on but we know we know
that Rainer is accusing Marvin of
something pretty bad right so you can
kind of put two and two together um you
know it could be the body of a missing
person in other words um so this is a
chilling example of how pet Scott blurs
the line between the virtual and um real
life right so it turn it turns the game
into a kind of a a digital interrogation
tool
um and while it does seem to be the case
that Rainer created pet scop or at least
like the creepy portion of pet scop for
Marvin it is nonetheless the case that
pet scop functions in the radical
absence of its creator so this is
something I emphasized in the very last
analysis video I did on pet scop that
how how language functions in in the
radical absence of the speaker sometimes
right like that's kind of a unique
feature of language that I could put
like a Post-It note on something and
that would be uh a message for somebody
else that functions in my absence um
this is not something other animals can
do this is something only humans can do
thus far right
um so language
functions in the radical absence of the
speaker and a video game uh you know
likewise functions in the radical
absence of the game's Creator right
because it's strongly implied that
Daniel Hammond is no longer around um I
think you know he kind of did himself in
uh due to his uh supposedly due to his
guilt right
um so new
participants are now undergoing this
kind of hellish process right like all
of their movements are being tracked so
this system was created to ostensibly to
uh try and interrogate Marvin right but
now it's TR backing everybody anybody
who plays the game um and so this is
rainer's Legacy he created like a mass
surveillance system um so this adds
another layer of complexity
um this kind of uh this kind of tracking
system
and it is interesting how the game uh
repurposes the players past movements in
its demo sequences uh with a Twist these
movements are
transcoded onto like a map that is in a
previous state right like
so um doors might be that were
previously closed might be open um
allowing the players past actions to
kind of navigate spaces that they
couldn't before uh this is really
interesting to me and it's not something
I've seen in any other work previously
um it I think this mechanic serves as a
metaphor for how past
actions can have unforeseen consequences
in new context so it's a it's a
commentary on memory and Trauma and
perhaps the inescapability of certain
patterns
um yeah this transcoding of movements
creates kind of a sense of uh temporal
disorientation where the past
infiltrates the present and it makes the
game feel sort of haunted by previous
interactions it's also fascinating and
somewhat ironic that Dominico
deliberately obscured parts of pet scp's
story because he knew YouTubers would
try to solve it right um and provide
clear explanation so it's kind of
interesting that it petscop is kind of
the antithesis of uh the typical
YouTuber doing a kind of uh you know uh
XY or Z explained right um it it resists
explanation um due to its inherent
ambiguity it's kind of a thesis like a
the
antithesis of a a sort of completion
this mindset in some sense
um
so you know by resisting straightforward
interpretation um the Creator preserves
the work's kind of dreamlike enigmatic
quality and it it does drive home for me
that anyone who is trying to treat this
like a
puzzle is missing the point right um and
that is that that's a conclusion I reach
at the end of my analysis but you know I
just I kind of want to um impress upon
you that you know merely because I've
made this observation that doesn't mean
I've solved it either right it's kind
it's kind of a par paradoxical thing
isn't it
um so I think petscop challenges us to
embrace ambiguity and and Find meaning
in process and experience itself rather
than um sort of binary black and white
thinking um and clear
answers uh but yeah uh revisiting pet
scop in a theater really did magnify
these themes for me and it reminded me
that pet scop you know isn't just a
puzzle to be
solved it's an experience um to be felt
and uh Paul's mechanical approach to the
game at the beginning uh and our own
Tendencies to try and dissect and
explain reflect how we often engage with
media um and maybe life itself and in
the end uh petcot remains a haunting
Elusive and difficult thing to neatly
categorize uh it is a testament to the
power of ambiguity in art and the
richness of embracing the unknown know
um it's a work that doesn't just tell a
story but engages Us in an ongoing
dialogue about
control uh systems
complicity uh yeah all of that stuff so
thank you for joining me as I revisit
this uh Revisited this strange
fascinating work I would love to hear
your thoughts uh and interpretations so
let me know what you think and until
next time take care
[Music]